coffee what a magical world where all
these different possibilities open for
us to enjoy an Exquisite beverage that
is shared amongst communities around the
world you first get into coughing you
get so excited you go I'm getting that
kimx I'm getting that V60 that air press
that French press and all of a
sudden that disgusting Taste of the cure
egg or than espresso is long
gone and now you're drinking freshly
roasted local coffees that you grind in
your burd grinder at home that retains
the Aromas and then you keep brewing and
you stumble into an online community and
you're like this is fun other people who
are nerding out about their coffee you
get on and you're
wow what they spent $27 on that bag of
coffee wait a second they're talking
about particle size
distribution they're using different
types of filters and talking about the
efficacy on the extraction oh my god
I've got to up my game and then before
you know it you're in the middle of gear
acquisition syndrome now you're watching
Lance Hedrick on YouTube that is so
weird and you're listening to all these
different theories that are thrown about
you're looking up research and you're
figuring out the new models on how heat
extracts and you've kind of lost the
passion you're like what the heck this
is really
[Music]
hard now that's one option of course the
other op option is you're into coffee
and uh you just bought your new gear and
you're wanting to know about coffee and
you're like oh my God this is all so
discombobulating what I'm seeing online
oh my God I don't even want to brew
coffee anymore it's too
terrifying I like to start by setting a
standard recipe that I kind of go to
every time so that's what we're going to
use as kind of our Baseline in this
video but of course I can change that
any way that I want I want to keep as
many static as possible things that I
don't think will have as big of an
effect on that Final Cup the things that
have huge effects on the final cup is
where I want to really concentrate my
time and
energy I pour for the Bloom three times
the weight of the coffee and I use a
pretty coarsely ground grind size and
then I will let it Bloom for anywhere
from 30 seconds to 2 minute that's one
of my variables I will play with and
then I pour the rest of the water in
because contact time is an important
variable I will sit there and watch it
and if it's seems like it's going pretty
quickly through the bloom well then I
may decide I'll add some manual
agitation to my second pore or I may
decide I'm going to split my second por
into two pores because the more pores
you make the more
agitation but what it is important to do
is to find a recipe that you feel is
good now I know that these Brewers
competitions these influencers and
everything even me have thrown a lot of
information into the pool and a lot of
pseudoscience along with it these pores
affect the strength of the coffee these
pores affect the sweetness these pores
affect the acidity that's not based on
anything except maybe one person's
experience on a certain
[Music]
coffee there's no such thing in coffee
as a very simple fix all okay if you
pour this amount of the coffee at this
roughness you're going to get this exact
experience in the cup and if this part
of the pour is poured this way you're
getting this exact experience in the cup
it doesn't work like
[Music]
that we don't need any extreme recipe
here find something that is easy
something that's very easily
manipulated my goal is never to hit 100%
of a coffee's potential because that's
going to take so much time and effort
and energy and a lot of coffee that I'm
going to be speeding through I mean yes
I would love to hit 100% And I'm going
to make my best educated guesses but I'm
not going to sit there and be
disappointed with a bad cup so I want to
find the fastest way to 80 % of that
Cup's full potential and then feel
confident that I'm getting a really good
cup out of that
coffee and then as the days go on and I
have the coffee make tweaks to
potentially better it and then maybe by
the end we're close to
100 this is not applied to everyone
there are going to be a few of you out
there who really enjoy nerding out and
getting 50 Brewers and this is obviously
not targeted at you you do you you
obviously feel very confident in your
approach to Brewing you likely have a
ton of confirmation bias win wink I
enjoyed playing with different Brewers
but most every day I I use the same
thing the V60 and it's because I want to
make it easy I want to make something I
know is going to taste good and I want
to make something that I can change
different variables on the
flight pick a two or three poor recipe
and keep that as your Baseline and then
what we're going to do is we need to
understand some of these different
variables but on a very base level just
so you can make little changes on the
fly or dayto day as you're brewing your
coffee
tap water unless you're in those areas
where it's insanely good tap water where
you don't have a lot of different
nasties in there please consider at
least using like a brda or something or
if you have capability to install like
reverse osmosis or something along those
lines just take into account that water
is one of the biggest effects on your
coffee and it's such an easy fix that
will immediately improve your coffee I
just please do this for me
okay so ratio will dictate the strength
of your cup there are other things it
can do obviously but for the most part
it's going to dictate the strength and
the extraction yield of your cup if you
have everything the same and you do one
cup to a 1 to 15 ratio one cup to a 1 to
17 ratio the 1 to 15 will have a higher
concentration meaning literally it'll be
a thicker coffee and a lower extraction
whereas the one to 17 will be the
opposite it'll have a lower
concentration but a higher extraction
the big thing I recommend thinking about
when you're looking at TDs is how thick
are you wanting your beverage the
shorter the ratio the thicker it will be
relative to a bigger ratio at the same
grind setting and everything else held
constant I like to stick to right at a 1
to 17 maybe a little under and I don't
really budge with it unless I'm doing a
decaf in which case I go down to 1 to 15
and that's because there's just a lot
less goodies to extract from decaf or if
I'm using a really old coffee I'll go
down to maybe a 1 to
15 the finer you grind you're going to
get a much easier route to bitterness in
your cup also an easier route to
channeling but the course you go you
have an easier route to undere
extraction easier route to low contact
time but really only nicer Grinders will
give you a really fast draw down at
coarser
grounds lower quality Grinders even at
coar grounds will take a while so it all
depends on the quality of your
extraction as it's going through that
bed I tend to prefer corser grounds
across all of my Brew methods it's very
rare I go on the finer side and when I
say corser I mean proper course like I'm
going bigger than like that like the
sugar that you have on the table you
know that Grandma's house for
Thanksgiving I'm going like big old
particles I'm going like River Rocks for
the most
part if I'm using say a zp6 or an -43
with my Brew burst and I say oh the best
recipe is this but you're sitting at
home with like a common Dante you're
sitting at home with like a norm core
hand grinder those particles
distributions are so vastly different
you're not getting anywhere near near
the same results there's like no
allaround recipes you essentially need
to find something as a Baseline and
tweak it to make it your own
recipe temperature the higher the
temperature the more extraction
potential in the sense that the water
can more easily penetrate the grounds
the lower the temperature it's not as
easy it takes more time in order for it
to do the same effect as higher temps
does that mean we need higher temps for
light roasts in a way if you want it to
extract to a certain degree that being
said I used to preach you know that you
should Brew off boiling but I found over
the years that even with super lightly
roasted coffees I get better cups at 95
degrees than at 99 they tend to be less
bitter and I can still get all the good
things I enjoy about the 99 degree cup
and a 95 degree cup without the
bitterness it does seem that when you go
really high you might be unlocking some
things that will come out earlier in the
process than later if you had a lower
temperature so maybe you can cut the
Brew off before some of that negative uh
extraction occurs
there is some evidence on when things
come out that I've discussed in the past
by Dr s SM but for now I don't ever
really go above 95 the darker the roast
the lower the temperature and decaf I
lower the temperature I never go above
about 89 even with the lightest roasted
decaf
coffees Brewer is obviously important
but honestly I approach most all Brewers
very similarly the only thing that I
kind of approach differently is I do
tend to do wet wdt whenever I'm not
using using a cone Brewer it seems to be
really easy to kind of just scratch
through the bed to ensure it's evenly
wetted I grind coarsely enough that the
water wants to run through unless I'm
using one of those flat bottom Brewers
like the SARS one that you can twist
shut the bottom of that Brewer so it
doesn't lose the water uh through that
bloom there's a lot of thought on
cutting down your Bloom and it improves
aromatics or increasing your Bloom and
it does this having no Bloom and it does
this now I've tried all of these
different things things and I've not
seen anything consistent across roast
levels different styles of coffees or
anything in my opinion for Simplicity
sake I stick with a one to three every
time I don't really mess with it maybe
I'll do a little less than it I don't
really pay too much attention if I have
20 grams of coffee maybe I'll do 50 gam
Bloom maybe I'll do 55 I just want it
fully wetted and I want to make sure I
hit every part of the bed I kind of stop
and normally with a controlled poure
that's about three times the the size
Bloom time this is fully dependent on
the how gaseous it is and how much
extraction it needs there's a lot to
take into account with blooming but of
course you can start off with just
across the board a 45 second bloom or a
1 minute bloom or a 30 second
Bloom as you understand the bloom more
maybe after you pour the bloom and you
watch How It's acting you can decide on
the Fly okay I'm going to extend it 30
seconds now when you have a grinder
that's really low quality you're likely
getting two big issues a lot of Boulders
are being produced so particles that are
much bigger than the average particle
size and a whole lot of fines are being
produced which are teeny tiny little
bitty cutie patootie particles whenever
you pour more and more and more it's
good for the boulders because you're
trying to extract more and it's hard for
the water to really get inside of that
but with those little teeny tiny cutie
patootie particles well you're just
getting them to be more and more flushed
into the filter and potentially clogging
it causing a lot of no
no but also the more you're pouring that
bed is being frivolous it's coming up
and then it settled back down then every
time you pour it goes up and down up and
down and every time it does that the
bigger particles go up higher and the
fines want to drop immediately and so
they keep getting into the filter and
then essentially if at the end you were
to scoop out all the big particles there
would be a big old film of those fines
around the edges meaning a lot of those
are getting through every time you have
a bare Kettle pour onto your filter
those paper filters aren't perfect they
allow particles to get
through I prefer fewer pores to more
pores because I don't want to cause that
much agitation I don't want to allow as
much of those particulates to get to
through to the Final
Cup in fact the Mellow drip which is uh
you know that little that little cute
shower screen that you pour through that
was actually created to negate use
having to rely on bare Kettle pores
because of the amount of little fines
and particles that get through the cup
that can obfuscate the pallet so people
will use that mellow drip in order to
not upset the bed because this is such a
big issue
I tend to do little circle right in the
middle and I do a little circle just to
kind of allow for an excavation down to
the centermost part of my cone since I'm
using a V60 and allowing as much
flipping and agitation as possible while
I'm doing it that being said if I
realize that the draw down is slow I may
just do a center pour and not really
move it and I may do a slight little
shake at the end to kind of settle the
bed because that won't be a ton of
agitation but that allows for more even
draw down when you kind of settle that
bed
so maybe I see it's drawing down quite
slowly then I just you know lamin or
flow to the end even though I'm normally
turbulent so there are a lot of
different things you can change once you
understand these variables this is going
to affect the you know the the clogging
of the filter paper it's going to affect
the type of agitation you're giving to
the bottom part of the bed so these
things are good to take into account
depending on your drain through
speed I do tend to shake kind kind of a
lot just a little shake to make sure
that bed gets level I don't want my bed
to look like this while it's was pouring
in the center cuz that's going to tell
me that the water was draining through
and hitting parts of the bed a lot more
than others especially that last little
bit when parts of the bed may be already
surfaced and the water's still touching
other parts little Shake flattens It Out
good to
go yeah manual agitation can also
include you know wdt or uh using a spoon
being too aggressive can cause clogging
but again it depends on the coffee
you're using and it depends on how the
water drains through during that bloom
and whether or not you think you need to
add a lot of that
agitation can just say I want to pour
every time the bed's fully drained or
you can be strick and be like every 45
seconds I'm going to pour which is a
very competition style way of doing
things doesn't mean it's right but they
have to do it because they get docked
off if they don't pour exactly the same
way on all three cups so remember do not
idolize competitions there are so many
roles they're playing for the points
it's not real
life my attempt with this video was to
to make what is complicated more
simplistic but I noticed as I was doing
it I was still making it complicated but
also hopefully making it a bit
entertaining and a bit more simplistic
so that you can come away from this
video being encouraged not frightened
but encouraged that this is not that
hard what you need to do is find that
base recipe understand it's not going to
be perfect the first time make minor
tweaks with the bigger variables before
you get into the minutia you don't need
to worry about your water chemistry
unless you're not filtering your water
in which case please please do that we
need to get a good cup first so we're
going to play with our grind size we're
going to play with our ratio which is
probably the first thing I'd recommend
if you have a decent grind size we're
going to play with our water temperature
but only in steps of like 3 to 6°
Centigrade okay it needs to be big steps
little teeny tiny steps you're likely
not going to tell the difference and
we're going to play around with those
things then you can go to like Bloom
time or you can go to like Bloom
temperature or you can go to like
getting a different grinder and playing
around with two different particle
distributions but but until you get a
solid cup there's no need to venture out
you don't need to over complicate it I
promise you with just the main variables
you can get an incredible cup we have
just tended to over complicate things as
we get really into coffee but listen
you're going to do great coffee is fun
we have communities online yes we over
complicate things yes we idealize
certain things yes we talk out of our
butts very often but it's all fun all
right if you've watched this far put
down below I'm a Crazy Coffee cook and I
crave Crazy Coffee and that will show us
that we have a community of Crazy Coffee
CS that crave crazy C Crazy Coffee say
that 10 times fast anyway thank you so
much you can check out my patreon down
below or the Instagram or whatever you
know if you hit the like And subscribe
that's great if you don't it's cool it
is what it is but anyway I had a lot of
fun today I hope that you did as well
and until next time I hope that you bre
something tasty today and cheers